Hi guys, I'm back with another exciting lesson.
Today's lesson has three parts.
Part 1.
Introduction to sentence completion in IELTS reading.
Part 2.
Steps for sentence completion in IELTS reading.
Part 3.
Practice.
This lesson aims to help you understand the
format of sentence completion in IELTS reading.
Remember, understand and apply steps for sentence completion
in IELTS reading.
Practice sentence completion in IELTS reading with the
topic of science and technology.
Let's get started with the first part.
Sentence completion is a question type in which
some incomplete sentences are provided and candidates are
required to fill in the blanks with exact
words taken from the reading passage.
This question type is not too challenging but
we still need to stay focused to find
the suitable information to fill in the blanks.
In the previous lesson, you learned the steps
for completion questions in IELTS reading.
So, let's do the interactive question below to
see if you remember them.
Do you remember all the steps?
We're going to apply them to handle the
reading passage below.
Let's start with the first step.
Step 1.
Read the question's requirement carefully.
Reading the question's requirement will provide us with
the following two pieces of information.
Type of completion question.
Word limit for each blank.
With this requirement, what information can we have?
The requirement has the phrase "Complete the sentences below"
So, this is the sentence completion question type.
Furthermore, we are required to choose no more
than two words which means we are not
allowed to write more than two words for each blank.
After understanding the question's requirement, we'll move to...
Read each question carefully and predict the answer.
As stated in the previous lessons, every time
you handle a question, you should read it
carefully to use prediction skill.
Predict about the answer you need to write.
Prediction skill is very important in completion questions
because making detailed predictions will help us find
the information faster and more correctly.
Here are some aspects to consider when you
make predictions about the answer.
Grammar and word form.
Does the blank need a noun, verb, adjective
or any other word form?
If the answer is a noun, is it a singular or plural noun?
If it is a verb, is it to verb?
Verb ending with ing or verb infinitive?
Content.
If it is a noun, is it a noun referring to a person?
Or a noun referring to an object?
Or a noun referring to an event?
If it is an adjective, is it an
adjective describing personalities or objects?
Now, let's apply our prediction skills to the
first three questions of our passage.
Homeschooling – Learning Beyond the Classroom.
Remember, making detailed predictions helps us find the
information faster and more accurately.
Question one.
Homeschooling allows children to study
without attending a .... school.
For grammar and word form, we are looking
for an adjective because the blank is placed
directly before the noun school.
As for content, the answer will likely be
a word that describes a type or category
of school that is different from homeschooling.
Question two.
Homeschooled students can choose the most suitable ...
For grammar and word form, the blank follows
the adjective suitable, so we need a noun.
It could be a singular, plural or uncountable noun.
For content, the answer should refer to something
that can be chosen or customized in a
homeschooling environment.
For example, a time, a place or a program.
For question three, students become more confident and
stay ... through personalized learning.
For grammar and word form, the blank follows
the linking verb stay and is connected by
the conjunction and to confident.
Therefore, we need an adjective that is parallel
in meaning to confident.
The answer will be a word describing a
positive mental state or feeling a student has while learning.
Now it's your turn to apply this prediction skill
to the remaining questions.
With step three, apply scanning skills to locate information.
In the previous lessons, we learned three steps
for scanning.
Number one.
Identify keywords in questions.
We have two main types of keywords.
Unchangeable keywords.
Proper nouns, acronyms, numbers, scientific or academic terms.
Changeable keywords.
Nouns, verbs, adjectives, adverbs.
Because they are often keywords
carrying the main content of the sentence.
Let's identify keywords in sentence one.
Homeschooling allows children to study
without attending a ... school.
Homeschooling is a changeable keyword noun.
but since it's the main topic of the text,
it will appear everywhere in the passage.
Attending and school.
These are changeable keywords.
Without, this is a crucial logic keyword that
shows a negative relationship not doing something.
Next step for scanning is identify scanning words
among keywords.
Unchangeable keywords.
Compounds.
Long words.
In this sentence, attending and school are our
best scanning words.
While homeschooling is the title, we need to
find the specific part of the text that
mentions not going to a certain type of school.
Next, we need to find keywords or synonyms
in the passage.
Tip one, look for the scanning words first.
Tip two, be ready for synonyms.
When we scan the first paragraph, we find
homeschooling is a way of learning where children
study at home instead of going to a traditional school.
The phrase without attending in the question is
a synonym for instead of going to in the text.
The word school matches perfectly.
This narrows our focus to just this one sentence.
Now we can move to the final step.
Now please read that sentence carefully and do step four.
Find and fill in the answer.
Based on the predictions in step two,
we will find the correct answer from the sentence
we've just scanned and then write it on
the answer sheet if you take the paper-based test
or copy and paste the answer directly onto the blanks
if you take the computer-based test.
Based on our previous prediction, we needed an
adjective to describe the school.
We look at the word right before the
word school in the text.
We select the word traditional.
If you are on a computer-based test,
you can copy-paste it.
If on paper, write it clearly on your answer sheet.
After step four, to be more careful, you
should do an additional step which is to check the answer.
You should check whether the word or phrase
you filled in meets the following criteria.
Does it satisfy the word limit?
Does it match the word form and grammar?
Does it match the meaning of the sentence?
Now it is your turn to practice these
steps with sentence two.
Follow your study plan, study hard, and enhance
your vocabulary to improve your reading comprehension skills.
Goodbye everyone.
See you in the next lesson.